access. CHAPTER 10 When his servant entered, he looked at him steadfastly and wondered if he had
thought of peering behind the screen. The man was quite impassive and
waited for his orders. Dorian lit a cigarette and walked over to the glass
and glanced into it. He could see the reflection of Victor’s face perfectly. It
was like a placid mask of Civility There was nothing to be afraid
of, there. Yet he thought it best to be on his guard. Speaking very slowly, he told
him to tell the housekeeper that he wanted to see her, and then to go to the
Fram maker and ask him to send two of his men round at once. It seemed to him
that as the man left the room his eyes wandered in the direction of the
screen. Or was that merely his own fancy?
After a few moments, in her black silk dress, with old-fashioned thread mittens
on her wrinkled hands, Mrs. Leaf bustled into the library. He asked her for the key of the
school room The old school room Mr. Dorian?” she exclaimed. “Why, it is full of dust. I must
get it arranged and put straight before you go into it. It is not fit for you to
see, sir. It is not, indeed.” “I don’t want it put put straight,
Leaf. I only want the key.” “Well, sir, you’ll be covered with
cobwebs if you go into it. Why, it hasn’t been open for nearly 5 years— —not since
his lordship died.” He winced at the mention of his grandfather. He had
hateful memories of him. “That does not matter,” he answered. “I simply want to see
the place— —that is all. Give me the key.” “And here is the key, sir,” said the old
lady, going over the contents of her bunch with tremulously uncertain hands.
“Here is the key. I’ll have it off the
bunch in a moment. But you don’t think of living up there, sir, and you so
comfortable here?” “No, no,” he cried petulantly. “Thank you, Leaf. That will
do.” She lingered for a few moments, and was garous over some detail of the
household. He sighed and told her to manage things as she thought best. She
left the room, wreathed in smiles. As the door closed, Dorian put the
key in his pocket and looked around the room. His eye fell on a large, purple
satin covet heavily embroidered with gold, a splendid piece of late 17th
century Venetian work that his grandfather had found in a convent near
bolognia Yes, that would serve to wrap the dreadful thing in. It had perhaps
served often as a pole for the dead. Now it was to hide something that had a
corruption of its own, worse than the corruption of death itself— —something
that would breed horrors and yet would would never die. What the worm was to the
corpse, his sins would be to the painted image on the canvas. They would mar its
beauty and eat away its grace. They would defile it and make it shameful. And yet
the thing would still live on. It would be always alive. He shuddered, and for a moment he
regretted that he had not told Basil the true reason why he had wished to hide
the picture away. Basil would have helped him to resist Lord Henry’s influence, and
the still more poisonous influences that came from his own
temperament. The love that he bore him— —for it was really love— —had nothing in it
that was not noble and intellectual. It was not that mere physical admiration of
beauty that is born of the senses and that dies when the senses tire. It was
such love as Michelangelo had known, and montin and vinl man and Shakespeare
himself. Yes, Basil could have saved him.
But it was too late now. The past could always be annihilated. Regret, denial, or
forgetfulness could do that. But the future was inevitable. There were
passions in him that would find their terrible outlet, dreams that would make
the shadow of their evil real. He took up from the couch the great
purple and gold texture that covered it, and, holding it in his hands, passed behind the
screen. Was the face on the canvas Vier than before? It seemed to him that it was unchanged,
and yet his loathing of it was intensified. Gold hair, blue eyes, and rose
red lips— —they all were there. It was simply the expression that had altered.
That was horrible in its cruelty.
Compared to what he saw in it of censure or rebuke, how shallow Basil’s reproaches
about cibil van had been!— !—how shallow, and of what little account! His own soul was
looking out at him from the canvas and calling him to judgment A look of pain
came across him, and he flung the rich Paul over the picture. As he did so, a
knock came to the door. He passed out as his servant entered. “The persons are here
mure He felt that the man must be got
rid of at once. He must not be allowed to know where the picture was being taken
to. There was something sly about him, and he had thoughtful, treacherous
eyes. Sitting down at the writing table he scribbled a note to Lord Henry, asking
him to send him round something to read and reminding him that they were to meet
at 8:15 that evening. “Wait for an answer,” he said, handing it to him, “and show the
men in here.” In two or 3 minutes there was another knock, and Mr hubard himself, the
celebrated framemaker of South odley Street, came in with a somewhat roughl looking young
assistant. Mr hubard was a flid red whiskered little man, whose admiration
for art was considered considerably tempered by the inveterate impecuniosity
of most of the artists who dealt with him. As a rule, he never left his
shop. He waited for people to come to him.
But he always made an exception in favor of Dorian Gray. There was something about
Dorian that charmed everybody. It was a pleasure even to see him. “What can I do
for you, Mr. Gray?” he said, rubbing his fat freckled hands. “I thought I would do
myself the honor of coming round in person. I I've just got a beauty of a
frame, sir. Picked it up at a sale. Old Florentine. Came from font Hill I believe.
Admirably suited for a religious subject, Mr.
Gray.” “I am so sorry you have given yourself the trouble of coming round, Mr
hubard I shall certainly drop in and look at the
frame— —though I don’t go in much at present for religious art— —but today I
only want a picture carried to the top of the house for me. It is rather heavy,
so I thought I would ask you to lend me a couple of your
men.” “No trouble at all, Mr. Gray. I delighted to be of any service to you.
Which is the work of art, sir?” “This,” replied Dorian, moving the screen back.
“Can you move it, covering an all, just as
it is? I don’t want it to get scratched going upstairs.” “There will be no difficulty, sir,”
said the genial frame maker beginning, with the aid of his assistant, to unhook
the picture from the long brass chains by by which it was
suspended. “And, now, where shall we carry it to, Mr.
Gray?” “I will show you the way, Mr hubard if you will kindly follow me. Or perhaps
you had better go in front. I am afraid
it is right at the top of the house. We
will go up by the front staircase, as it is
wider.” He held the door open for them, and they passed out into the hall and began
the ascent. The elaborate character of the frame had made the picture extremely
bulky, and now and then, in spite of the obsequious protests of Mr hubard who had
the true tradesman’s spirited dislike of seeing a gentleman doing anything useful,
Dorian put his hand to it so as to help them. “Something of a load to carry, sir,”
gasped the little man when they reached the top landing. And he wiped his shiny
forehead. “I am afraid it is rather heavy,” murmured Dorian as he unlocked the door
that opened into the room that was to keep for him the curious secret of his
life and hide his soul from the eyes of men. He had not entered the place for
more than four years— —not, indeed, since he had used it first as a play room when he
was a child, and then as a study when he grew somewhat older. It was a large,
well-proportioned room, which had been specially built by the last Lord Kelo
for the use of the little grandson whom, for his strange likeness to his mother,
and also for other reasons, he had always hated and desired to keep at a distance.
It appeared to Dorian to have but little changed. There was the huge Italian
casson with its fantastically painted panels and its tarnished guilt moldings
in which he had so often hidden himself as a boy. There the satin wood bookcase
filled with his dogar school books On the wall behind it was hanging
the same ragged Flemish tapestry where a faded king and queen were playing chess
in a garden, while a company of hawkers rode by, carrying hooded birds on their
gauntleted wrists. How well he remembered it all! Every moment of his lonely childhood
came back to him as he looked around He recalled the stainless purity of his
boyish life, and it seemed horrible to him that it was here the fatal portrait
was to be hidden away. How little he had thought, in those dead days, of all that
was in store for him! But there was no other place in the
house so secure from prying eyes as this.
He had the key, and no one else could enter it. Beneath its purple pole the
face painted on the canvas could grow bestial Soden and
unclean. What did it matter? No one could see it. He himself would not see it. Why
should he watch the hideous corruption of his soul? He kept his youth— —that was
enough. And, besides, might not his nature grow finer, after all? There was no reason
that the future should be so full of shame.
Some love might come across his life, and purify him, and shield him from those
sins that seem to be already stirring in spirit and in flesh— —those curious
unpictured sins whose very mystery lent them their subtlety and their charm.
Perhaps someday the cruel look would have passed away from the scarlet
sensitive mouth, and he might show to the world Basil hallwoods
masterpiece. No; that was impossible. Hour by hour, and week by week, the thing upon
the canvas was growing old. It might escape the hideousness of sin, but the
hideousness of age was in store for it.
The cheeks would become hollow or flaccid. Yellow crows feet would creep
round the fading eyes and make them horrible. The hair would lose its
brightness, the mouth would gape or droop, would be foolish or gross, as the mouths
of old men are. There would be the wrinkled throat, the cold blue veined
hands, the twisted body, that he remembered in the grandfather
who had been so stern to him in his boyhood. The picture had to be concealed.
There was no help for it. “Bring it in, Mr hubard please,” he said,
wearily, turning round. “I am sorry I kept you so long. I was thinking of something
else.” “Always glad to have a rest, Mr. Gray,” answered the Fram maker who was still
gasping for breath. “Where shall we put it, sir?” “Oh,
anywhere. Here: this will do. I don’t want to have it hung up. Just lean it against
the wall.
Thanks.” “Might one look at the work of art, sir?” Dorian started. “It would not interest
you, Mr hubard he said, keeping his eye on the man. He felt ready to leap upon him
and fling him to the ground if he dared to lift the gorgeous hanging that
concealed the secret of his life. “I Shan trouble you anymore now I'm much obliged
for your kindness in coming round.” “Not at all, not at all, Mr. Gray.
Ever ready to do anything for you, sir.” And Mr hubard tramped downstairs,
followed by the assistant, who glanced back at Dorian with a look of shy wonder
in his rough uncomely face. He had never seen anyone so marvelous When the sound of their
footsteps had died away, Dorian locked the door and put the key in his pocket.
He felt safe now. No one would ever look upon the horrible thing. No but his would
ever see his shame. On reaching the library, he found
that it was just after 5:00 and that the tea had been already brought
up. On a little table of dark perfumed wood thickly encrusted with Naka a
present from Lady Radley, his guardian’s wife, a pretty professional invalid, who
had spent the preceding winter in Cairo, was lying a note from Lord Henry, and
beside it was a book bound in yellow paper, the cover slightly torn and the edges
soiled. A copy of the third edition of The St james' Gazette had been placed on
the tea tray It was evident that Victor had returned. He wondered if he'd met the
men in the hall as they were leaving the house and had wormed out of them what
they had been doing. He would be sure to miss the picture— —had no doubt missed it
already, while he had been laying the tea things The screen had not been set back,
and a blank space was visible on the wall. Perhaps some night he might find
him creeping upstairs and trying to force the door of the
room. It was a horrible thing to have a
spy in one’s house. He had heard of rich men who had been blackmailed all their
lives by some servant who had read a letter, or overheard a conversation, or
picked up a card with an address, or found beneath a pillow a withered flower
or a shred of crumpled lace. He sighed, and having poured himself out some tea,
opened Lord Henry’s note.
It was simply to say that he sent him round the evening paper, and a book that
might interest him, and that he would be at the club at
8:15 He opened The St. James’s languidly, and looked through it. A red pencil mark
on the fifth page caught his eye. It drew attention to the following
paragraph inquest ON AN actress An inquest was held this morning at the
Bell Tavern hawton Road, by Mr. Danby, the District Coroner, on the body of cibil
vain a young actress recently engaged at the Royal Theater Halburn A verdict of death by
misadventure was returned. Considerable sympathy was expressed for the mother of
the deceased, who was greatly affected during the giving of her own evidence,
and that of Dr Burl who had made the postmortem examination of the
deceased. He frowned, and tearing the paper in two, went across the room and flung the pieces
away. How ugly it all was! And how horribly real ugliness made things! He
felt a little annoyed with Lord Henry for having sent him the report. And it
was certainly stupid of him to have marked it with red pencil. Victor might
have read it. The man knew more than enough English for
that. Perhaps he had read it and had begun to suspect something. And, yet, what did it
matter? What had Dorian Gray to do with cibil Vain's death? There was nothing to
fear. Dorian Gray had not killed her. His eye fell on the yellow book that Lord
Henry had sent him. What was it, he wondered. He went towards the little
pearl colored octagonal stand that had always looked to him like the work of
some strange Egyptian bees that rought in silver, and taking up the volume, flung
himself into an armchair and began to turn over the leaves. After a few minutes minutes he
became absorbed. It was the strangest book that he had ever read. It seemed to
him that in exquisite rment and to the delicate sound of flutes, the sins of the
world were passing in dumb show before him. Things that he had dimly dreamed of
were suddenly made real to him. Things of which he had never dreamed were gradually
revealed. It was a novel without a plot and with only one character, being, indeed
simp a psychological study of a certain young Parisian who spent his life trying
to realize in the 19th century all the passions and modes of thought that
belong to every century except his own, and to sum up, as it were, in himself the
various moods through which the world Spirit had ever passed, loving for their mere
artificiality those renunciations that men have unwisely called virtue, as much
as those natural rebellions that wise men still call sin. The St sty in which
it was written was that curious jeweled style, vivid and obscure at once, full of
argut and of archaisms, of technical expressions and of elaborate paraphrases,
that characterizes the work of some of the finest artists of the French school of
symbolists There were in it metaphors as monstrous as orchids and as subtle in
color The life of the senses was described in the terms of mystical
philosophy. One hardly knew at times when whether one was reading the spiritual
ecstasies of some medieval saint or the morbid confessions of a modern sinner. It
was a poisonous book. The heavy odor of incense seemed to cling about its pages
and to trouble the brain. The mere cadence of the sentences, the subtle
monotony of their music, so full as it was of complex refrains and movements
elaborately repeated, produced in the mind of the lad, as he passed from
chapter to chapter, a form of revery a malady of dreaming, that made him
unconscious of the falling day and creeping shadows. Cloudless, and pierced by one
solitary star, a copper green sky gleamed through the windows. He read on by its one light till
he could read no more. Then, after his valet had reminded him several times of
the lateness of the hour, he got up, and going into the next room, placed the book
on the little Florentine table table that always stood at his bedside and began to dress for
dinner. It was almost 9:00 before he reached the club, where he found Lord
Henry sitting alone, in the morning room looking very much
bored. “I am so sorry, Harry,” he cried, “but really it is entirely your fault. That
book you sent me so fascinated me that I forgot how the time was going.” “Yes, I
thought you would like it,” replied his host, rising from his chair. “I didn’t say
I liked it, Harry. I said it fascinated me.
There is a great difference.” “Ah, you have discovered that?” murmured Lord Henry. And
they passed into the dining